Cooper, Robertson & Partners Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Cooper, Robertson & Partners records
1979-2008
MS 1991
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
57.5
22 boxes
9,115.5
The records, dated 1979 to 2008, consist of drawings, press clippings, reports, photographs, and other project-related materials for a portion of the architectural work undertaken by the New York firm Cooper, Robertson & Partners. The drawings include sketches, schematics, site plans, and working and record drawings. The collection also comprises press materials pertaining to the firm's two founding partners, Alexander Cooper and Jaquelin Robertson.
Cooper, Robertson & Partners
Biographical / Historical
Cooper, Robertson & Partners (CRP) is a New York-based architecture and urban design firm founded in 1979 as Alexander Cooper Associates. The firm became Cooper Eckstut Associates in 1981, Alexander Cooper+ Partners in 1986, and finally Cooper, Robertson & Partners in 1988, when longtime colleague Jaquelin Robertson joined the firm. Both Cooper (BA 1958; MArch 1962) and Robertson (BA 1955; MArch 1961) are graduates of Yale University. CRP has carried out significant commissions for cultural and academic institutions, public agencies, entertainment companies, and developers of new communities. CRP is also known for its high-end residential work. The principals of CRP combine significant experience in government, teaching, and academic administration with private practice, as well as acting as representatives for both public and private development clients.
Within the firm's portfolio is the master plan for Battery Park City in New York City, the Framework for Campus Planning for Yale University, the plan for Allston at Harvard University, Columbia University's School of Social Work, MoMA QNS, the Ethical Culture Fieldston School, Duke University Cancer Center, Charleston Visitors Center, Disney Celebration and WaterColor in Florida, as well as the design of Zuccotti Park in Lower Manhattan and the design of a new 32-acre waterfront park in Miami – a range of work that extends from cities to gardens. More recently, the firm has undertaken a number of projects aimed at strengthening the cultural and physical infrastructure of New York City, including designs for the new Whitney Museum of American Art, Hunter College's School of Social Work, the Harlem Village Academy, and continued work for the Metropolitan Museum of Art for whom the firm completed a Collections Master Plan. CRP has shaped master plans for six miles along Philadelphia's Delaware River waterfront, for Research Triangle Park in North Carolina, and for the Honeywell Corporate Campus in New Jersey, as well as designing several new homes and apartment renovations. CRP is also a member of the winning team for The City + The Arch + the River 2015 International Design competition in St. Louis.
Cooper, Robertson & Partners has received numerous design awards for its work and is the first firm to receive National American Institute of Architects Awards in both architecture and urban design in the same year.
Sources: Firm information courtesy of Cooper, Robertson & Partners
Arrangement
The projects are arranged by job number.
Scope and Contents
The records, dated 1979 to 2008, consist of drawings, press clippings, reports, photographs, and other project-related materials for a portion of the architectural work undertaken by the New York firm Cooper, Robertson & Partners. The drawings include sketches, schematics, site plans, and working and record drawings. The collection also comprises press materials pertaining to the firm's two founding partners, Alexander Cooper and Jaquelin Robertson.
Other Finding Aids
For a list of projects and boxes in which materials are located, please consult the Project Index.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Cooper, Robertson & Partners, 2012.
Conditions Governing Access
Some projects are restricted and require permission of the firm to access. See Project Index for details.
List of projects in collection
80003 Battery Park City
93003 Celebration
90029 New Albany Country Club
88035 Rose House
97019 WaterColor
97005 Yale Framework for Campus Planning
11021 Zuccotti Park
Architecture -- Designs and plans; Architecture -- United States; Battery Park (New York, N.Y.); Celebration (Fla.); Cooper, Alexander, 1936-; Robertson, Jaquelin Taylor, 1933-; Cooper, Eckstut Associates; Cooper, Robertson & Partners
- Project records
  Other Finding Aids
  For a list of projects and boxes in which materials are located, please consult the Project Index.
  - Battery Park City, 1979-1982
    Scope and Contents
    Job number: 80003
    Job location: New York, NY
    Project type: Urban Design, MP
    - Press Files (Box 1)
    - Reports and Books (Box 2)
  - Celebration, 1997
    Job number: 93003
    Job location: Celebration, FL
    Project type: Urban Design, MP, New Town Plan
    - Press Files (Box 2, Box 8)
    - Reports and Books (Box 2)
    - Drawings: Sketches (Box 2)
    - Drawings: Schematic/Design Development (Box 2)
    - Working Drawings: Architectural/Structural (Box 5, Box 7)
    - Drawings: Site/Landscape (Box 4–8)
    - Drawings: As-Built/Record (Box 5)
  - New Albany Country Club, 1991-1993
    Job number: 90029
    Job location: Columbus, OH
    Project type: Architecture, Urban Design
    - Press Files (Box 3)
    - Drawings: Schematic/Design Development (Box 3, Box 11)
    - Working Drawings: Architectural/Structural (Box 9)
    - Drawings: Site/Landscape (Box 10–11, Folder 12)
    - Drawings: As-Built/Record (Box 4)
  - Private Residence, 1986
    Job number: 88035
    Job location: East Hampton, NY
    Project type: Architecture
    - Drawings: As-Built/Record (Box 13)
  - WaterColor, 2007
    Job number: 97019
    Job location: WaterColor, FL
    - Press Files (Box 3)
    - Drawings: Sketches (Box 3)
    - Drawings: Schematic/Design Development (Box 3, Box 14, Box 20)
    - Working Drawings: Architectural/Structural (Box 15–16, Box 18–19, Folder 17)
    - Drawings: Site/Landscape (Box 14)
    - Drawings: As-Built/Record (Box 20)
  - Yale Framework for Campus Planning, 2000
    Job number: 97005
    Job location: New Haven, CT
    Project type: Urban Design, MP, Education
    - Drawings: Sketches (Box 21)
    - Drawings: Schematic/Design Development (Box 21)
    - Working Drawings: Architectural/Structural (Box 21)
    - Drawings: Site/Landscape (Box 21)
  - Zuccotti Park, 2006
    Job number: 11021
    Project type: Urban Design, Public Space
    - Reports and Books (Box 3)
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Photographs, Negatives, and Slides (Box 3)
    - Working Drawings: Architectural/Structural (Box 22)
  - Press Files on Principals, 1979-2012
- Computer files (Box 23–25)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.